in this Illustrated tutorial I'm going
to show you how to type around a circle
so we're going to look at how to type
all the way around a circle and also how
to split that Circle so you can type on
the top and type on the bottom so let's
first make a circle basically what we're
going to do is click and hold on the
rectangle tool find the ellipse tool the
shortcut key is L and create a circle
out here while holding shift so it's a
perfect circle so we'll create that
Circle I'm going to create a second one
by holding alt or option on your
keyboard and just clicking and dragging
to duplicate this is because we're going
to look at two examples here now the
first one over here if we press the T
key on our keyboard for the type tool
you can see that as the T in your tools
panel over here we can actually type on
this circle and we could start by
clicking on it anywhere actually in this
case it might type on the inside so I
might make sure I click and hold and
instead of maybe it choosing area type
I'm going to type on a path and now any
anywhere I click on this circle is going
to be the starting point of my text I'm
going to go ahead and fill this in with
some placeholder text just by going up
to type down to fill with placeholder
text and now you can see that it is
typed around a circle I can increase the
font size so that we can actually see
this and now that we have an in and an
out point and you can drag these forward
and backward to decide where exactly
that type starts on your circle you can
kind of rotate that text around the
circle so if I wanted to start it here
at the top and also end at the top I
could drag the in and out points to the
same spot here now there's a few options
as well with this so if we go back up to
type we can see a type on a path dialog
or a kind of drop down menu and we
actually have some type on a path option
so you have some quick ones here if you
know what you want to do but I'm going
to go to type on a path options so here
we can flip it I'm going to preview this
so I can see what it does you can see
how flip it puts it on the other side of
the line
we can align it to the Ascender or the
descender or the baseline or even the
center of the text you can see how that
adjusts it I'm going to unflip it here
so we can actually see it so if you
wanted to type exactly in the middle of
the circle you created align it to the
center it's centered to the path
we also have spacing options but you can
adjust those spacing options in the
character panel and then the different
effects will do some different things
like skew your text or do a 3D ribbon
stair step will stair step the letters
and then gravity's an interesting one
that doesn't look like it does much with
this one but with other types of type on
a path lines and stuff it'll actually do
something but generally Rainbow's one I
leave it on and then you can align it
however you want here I'm going to hit
ok now what if we want to not just type
in a circle but we wanted to type in a
circle on the top and then on the bottom
have the letters be readable going in
the other direction kind of like a badge
icon what we need to do is split the
circle into two halves so to do that I'm
going to press C on my keyboard that is
the scissors tool you could click and
hold on the erasers tool to find the
scissors tool but the shortcut key is C
now I need to cut this path at these two
horizontal anchor points so I'm going to
click on this one I'm going to click on
this one over here
now what that does if I press the V key
for my move tool is it gives me a path
on the top and a path on the bottom you
can see that here when I just clicked
and dragged the top out a little bit
it's actually away from the bottom of
the circle so we have two different half
circles here now I'm going to press the
T key on my type tool and of course
click and type on a path here I'm going
to start it at this Anchor Point now if
you need to and it doesn't do this
correctly for you you can always click
and hold like we did before and go to
the type on a path tool just to make
sure you have that tool selected but I'm
going to click on the first Anchor Point
and we're going to just type in some
some words so I'm going to write type on
a path
so you can see how that goes around the
top side of the circle now of course
there's a few options like we talked
about if we grab our direct selection
tool I believe we can grab the in and
out points again so we could shift this
stuff actually I'm clicking all the
wrong things here maybe if I just grab
my selection tool yeah so there's a few
different if you can see the different
types of cursors I have here I'm not
sure you can but let's zoom in a little
bit so we can actually see this
so you see we have a line that sticks
out here and that's that end point that
I talked about so you can bring this
text to the middle of this circle just
by adjusting these in and out points so
this is the midpoint right here up top
there's a midpoint line and then this is
the out and this is the in which is the
beginning of your text so what I like to
do is drag this to the very end of the
Anchor Point like the first Anchor Point
drag that out to this Anchor Point and
then you can actually Center your text
up top by centering it in the paragraph
panel so we're going to align the text
to the center
now if you feel like that's off a little
bit you can still adjust these in and
out some if we click back on this you
can make some adjustments here and then
you have a midpoint that you can kind of
shift everything together just to get it
visually correct but if you drag these
to the beginning and end anchor points
you should be in a pretty good spot with
that text being on top now you could
type and make sure you have something
that goes all the way around or make
sure that you have a text size that
works that kind of goes all the way
around the circle but then what we would
do for the bottom is kind of do the same
thing so you want some type that goes in
the other direction this way so we're
going to click on this first Anchor
Point and I'm going to say type on
bottom
now we have an issue here right so it
looks like it's going the wrong way well
remember we went to those type on a path
settings up here in the type drop down
and we can go to type on a path options
and for this bottom part we can use that
flip option I'm going to preview it use
that flip option and you can see it put
us inside of the circle and flip the
text so the text is correct but to match
this outside of the circle path we need
to change where it's aligned to the path
so instead of Baseline we're going to do
Ascender which puts it on the outside of
the the path now to line this up a
little bit better my recommendation is
if you're doing this type of top and
bottom type on a path I would put it in
the center so I would align the path to
the center and hit OK and then we might
need to adjust some
font size down here if I get it selected
correctly might need to adjust this font
size so it fits on the bottom here and
then you can always adjust some of your
spacing and everything to make sure
everything fits correctly and then what
I would do is come to the top here do
the same thing kind of go to type on a
path settings adjust that so it's in the
center of the path again hit OK and then
you can make those same adjustments to
the Top If you need to but that is how
you can write text on the top and bottom
of your path here it looks like 100 is
the point size I changed that too and so
now the text on bottom matches the text
on top you can make sure these two
circles line up exactly intersected with
their anchor points again so that
actually is in a circle shape you can
put little you know now you can put
little decorations in here to make sure
that uh you know this thing kind of
looks like it's a badge or something and
then you can type in the center but
that's how you can put text on top and
on bottom now it's not on top and on
bottom of a circle what you have to do
is split that Circle but this is how you
can get that badge look and be able to
type either fully in a circle or type on
the top and the bottom of a circle and
those uh you have to use those type on a
path options to really get everything
situated correctly and typed in the
correct direction of your circle
and that's how you can type on a circle
here in Adobe Illustrator